Hello, it's fun to be here.
So the work I'm presenting
today, the title of it
is Attention Approximates
Sparse Distributed Memory,
and this was done
in collaboration
with Cengiz Pehlevan, and my
PhD advisor was Gabriel Kreiman.
So why should you
care about this work?
We show that the heuristic
attention operation
can be implemented
with simple properties
of high dimensional vectors in a
biologically plausible fashion.
So the transformer and
attention, as you know,
are incredibly powerful,
but they were heuristically
developed, and the softmax
operation in attention
is particularly important
but also heuristic.
And so, we show that the
intersection of hyperspheres
that is used in sparse
distributed memory closely
approximates the softmax
and attention more broadly,
both in theory and with
some experiments on train
transformers.
So you can see SDM,
Sparse Distributed Memory,
as preempting attention
by approximately 30 years.
It was developed back in 1988,
and what's exciting about this
is that it meets a high bar
for biological plausibility.
Hopefully, I have
time to actually get
into the wiring
of the cerebellum,
and how you can
map each operation
to part of the circuit there.
So first, I'm going to give an
overview of Sparse Distributed
Memory.
I have a transformer
attention summary,
but I assume that you guys
already know all of that.
We can get there and then decide
how deep we want to go into it.
I'll then talk about how
actually attention approximates
SDM.
Interpret the transformer more
broadly, and then hopefully,
there's time to go into SDM's
biological plausibility.
Also, I'm going
to keep everything
high level visual intuition,
and then go into the math.
But stop me, and please ask
questions, literally, whenever.
OK.
So Sparse Distributed
Memory is motivated
by the question of how the
brain can read and write
memories in order to later
retrieve the correct one.
And some considerations
that it takes into account
are high memory capacity,
robustness to query noise,
biological plausibility, and
some notion of fault tolerance.
SDM is unique from other
associative memory models
that you may be familiar
with, like hopfield networks.
Insomuch as it's
sparse, so it operates
at a very high
dimensional vector space,
and the neurons that
exist in this space
only occupy a very small
portion of possible locations.
It's also distributed, so
all read and write operations
apply to all nearby neurons.
It is actually, as a side
note, hopfield networks,
if you're familiar with
them, are a special case
of sparse distributed memory.
I'm not going to go
deep into that now,
but I have a blog post on it.
OK.
So first, we're going to look at
the write operation for sparse
distributed memory.
We're in this high dimensional
binary vector space.
We're using hamming distance
as our metric for now,
we'll move to continuous later.
And we have this
green pattern, which
is represented by the solid
dot, and the hollow circles
are these hypothetical neurons.
Also, think of everything
quite abstractly,
and then we'll map
to biology later.
So this pattern
has a write radius,
which is some hamming distance.
It activates all of the neurons
within that hamming distance,
and then here I just denote
that each of those neurons
are now storing
that green pattern,
and the green pattern
has disappeared.
So I'm keeping track
of its location
with this kind of
fuzzy hollow circle.
That will be relevant later.
So we're writing in another
pattern, this orange one,
and note here that neurons can
store multiple patterns inside
of them.
And formally, this is actually
a superposition or just
a summation of these
high dimensional vectors.
Because they're
high dimensional,
you don't have that
much crosstalk,
so you can get away with it.
But for now, you can
even just think of it
as a neuron can store
multiple patterns.
Finally, we have a third
pattern, this blue one.
We're writing in
another location.
And yeah, so again,
we're keeping
track of the original
pattern locations,
and they can be--
but they can be
triangulated from the nearby
neurons that are storing them.
And so we've written
in three patterns.
Now we want to read
from the system.
So I have this pink stars side.
It appears-- it has a
given It's represented
by a given vector, which
has a location in the space.
It activates nearby
neurons again,
but now the neurons
output the patterns
that they've stored previously.
And so you can see that
based upon its location,
it's getting four blue patterns,
two orange, and one green.
And it then does a
majority rule operation,
where it updates
towards whatever pattern
it sees the most.
So in this case because
blue is actually a majority,
it's just going to update
completely towards blue.
Again, I'll formalize
this more in a bit,
but this is really
to give you intuition
for the core operations of SDM.
So the key thing to relate
this back to attention
is actually to abstract
away the neurons that
are operating under the hood,
and just consider these circle
intersections.
And so what each of
these intersections
between the pink circle and
each of the write circles means
is the intersection
is the neurons that
both store that pattern
when it was written in,
and are now being read
from by the query.
And the size of
that intersection
corresponds to how
many patterns the query
is then going to read.
And so formally, we
define the number
of neurons in this
circle intersection
as the cardinality between
number of neurons in pattern,
number of neurons in query
and their intersection.
OK.
Are there any questions
at a high level
before I get more into the math?
I don't know if I can check.
Is it easy for me to check Zoom?
Nah, sorry, Zoom people,
I'm not going to check.
OK.
Are the neurons just randomly
distributed in the space?
Yes.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And there's later-- there's more
recent work that they can learn
and update their location
to [INAUDIBLE] manifold,
but in this, you can assume
that they're randomly
initialized binary high
dimensional vectors.
OK.
So this is the full
SDM update rule.
I'm going to break it down.
So the first thing that you do.
So this is for
reading, to be clear.
So you've already written
patterns into your neurons.
So the first thing you do
is you weight each pattern
by the size of its
circle intersection.
So the circle intersection
there for each pattern.
Then you sum over all of
the patterns that have
been written into the space.
So you're just doing a
weighted summation of them.
And then there's
this normalization
by the total number of
intersections that you have.
And finally, because
at least for now we're
working in this binary space,
you map back to binary,
just seeing if the values
are greater than one half.
OK.
How familiar are
people with attention?
I looked at like the
previous talks you've had,
they seem quite high level.
Like, can you guys write the
attention equation for me?
Is that like-- can I get
thumbs up if you can do that?
Yeah.
OK, I'm not like--
I'll go through this, but
I'll probably go through it
faster than otherwise.
So when I first made
this presentation, like,
this was the state of the
art for transformers, which
was like [INAUDIBLE] alphafold.
And so it's kind of funny
how far things have come now.
I don't need to tell you that
transformers are important.
So yeah.
I'm going to work
with this example.
Well, OK, I'm going to work
with this example here,
the cat sat on the blank.
And so in this setting,
we're predicting
the next token,
which hypothetically
is the word "mat."
And so there are four things
that the attention operation
is doing.
The first one up here
is it's generating
what are called keys
values and queries.
And again, I'll get into
the math in a second,
I'm just trying to keep
it high level first.
And then we're going
to compare our query
with each of the keys.
So the word "the," which is
closest to the word we're next
predicting is our
query, and we're
seeing how similar is
each of the key vectors.
We then, based upon
that similarity,
do this softmax normalization
so that all of the attention
weights sum to 1.
And then we sum
together their value
vectors to use to
propagate to the next layer
or uses our prediction.
And so at a high
level, you can think
of this as, like,
the query word "the"
is looking for nouns and
their associated verbs.
And so hypothetically,
it has a high similarity
with words like cat and
sat or they're keys.
So this then gives
large weight to the cat
and sat value vectors,
which get moved
to the next part of the network.
And the cat value
vector, hypothetically,
contains a superposition
of other animals,
like mice and maybe words
that rhyme with mat.
And the sat vector
also contains things
that are sat on, including mat.
And so what you actually
get from the value
vectors of paying attention to
cat and sat are like, 3 times
mat plus 1 times mouse
plus 1 times sofa.
This is again, like, a
totally hypothetical example,
but I'm trying to make the
point that you can extract
from your value vectors
things useful for predicting
the next token by paying
attention to specific keys.
So-- and I guess--
yeah, another thing here is
like what you pay attention to.
So cat and stat might
be different from what
you're actually extracting.
If you're paying
attention to your keys,
but you're getting
your value vectors out.
OK, so here is the full
attention equation.
The top line, I'm separating
out the projection matrices,
W subscript V [INAUDIBLE] and
q, and then the second one,
I just collapsed them into the
equation you are going to see.
And yeah, so
breaking this apart,
the first step here
is we compare--
we do a dot product between
our query vector and our keys.
This should actually
be a small q
and capital Q. Sorry for that.
And so yeah, we're doing
this dot product between them
to see--
get a notion of similarity.
We then apply the
softmax operation,
which is an exponential
over a sum of exponentials.
The way to think of
the softmax is it just
makes large values larger.
And this will be
important for the relation
to SDM, so I'll
spend a minute on it.
At the top here, I have
some hypothetical items--
index from 0 to 9.
And then the values for
each of those items.
In the second row, I just do
like a normal normalization
of them.
And so the top item
goes to a 30% value.
But if I instead
do a softmax, it
depends on the beta
[INAUDIBLE],, the softmax.
But the value becomes 0.6.
So it just-- it makes your
distributions peak year,
is kind of one way
of thinking of it.
And this is useful for
attention, because you only
want to pay attention to
the most important things,
or the things that are nearby.
And kind of ignore
stuff further away.
And so, once we've
applied our softmax,
we then just do a
weighted summation
of our value vector,
which actually
get extracted and propagate
to the next layer.
OK, so here's the full equation.
I went through that
a little bit quickly.
I'm happy to answer
questions on it,
but I think half of you of you
know it, half of you don't.
OK, so how does transformer
attention approximate sparse
distributed memory?
This 30-year-old thing that I've
said is biologically plausible.
So yeah?
It's, like, reasonable to accept
that that SDM is biologically
[INAUDIBLE]?
So I'm going to get to
that at the end, yeah.
And attention is also, like in
the sense of like all attention
mechanisms.
Is that like it was
invented by [INAUDIBLE]??
I think the attention
equation I'm showing here
was developed--
I mean, attention is all
you need was the highlight.
But Bengio has a
paper from 2015,
where it was actually
first written in this way.
Correct me if I'm wrong,
but I'm pretty sure--
Yeah, I mean, I guess
like this particular one.
That's why I was asking
the question, because--
No, it's a good question.
Like you show that two
different methods that
could be classified as
like attention proposals,
right, are like the same.
And like you said, one
of them is indifferent.
Yes, exactly, so I'll show
that has really nice mappings
to a circuit in the cerebellum
at the neuronal level.
And then, there's right now,
it's this link to attention.
And I guess you make a
good point that there
are other attention mechanisms.
This is the one that
has been dominant.
But I don't think that's
just a coincidence.
There's been a
bunch of-- computing
your softmax is
expensive, and there's
been a bunch of work like
the Linformer, et cetera,
et cetera, that tries to get
rid of the softmax operation.
And it's just done really badly.
Like there's a bunch of jokes
on Twitter now that it's like
a black hole for people to
try and get rid of softmax,
and you can't.
And so it seems like this--
and like other versions of it,
transformers just don't scale
as well in the same way.
And so there's something
important about this particular
attention equation.
But it goes the
other way, right?
Which is like, if this is
really important, then like SDM
is like actually like this.
So the thing that I
think is important
is that you have this
exponential weighting, where
you're really paying
attention to the things
that matter and you're
ignoring everything else.
And that is what
SDM approximates.
There might be better
equations, but the point
I was just trying to make
there is like the softmax does
seem to be important,
and this equation does
seem to be very successful.
And we haven't come up with
better formulations for it.
Yeah, no, that's
a great question.
OK, so it turns out that
sparse distributed memory,
as you move your query and your
pattern away from each other--
so you pull these circles apart,
the read and write circles--
the number of neurons that
are in this intersection,
in a sufficiently
high-dimensional space,
decays approximately
exponentially.
And so on this
right plot here, I
am pulling apart-- the
x-axis is me pulling apart
the blue and the pink circles.
And the y-axis is on a log
scale the number of neurons
that are in the intersection.
And so to the extent that
this is a linear plot on a log
scale, it's exponential.
And this is for a
particular setting,
where I have my 64
dimensional vectors, because I
used in GPT2, it holds across
a lot of different settings,
particularly higher
dimensions, which are now
used for bigger transformers.
OK, so I have this shorthand
for the circle intersection
equation.
And what I'll show is how
the circle intersection
is approximately exponential.
So we can write it with two
constants, c subscript 1
and subscript 2.
With the one outside, because
you're normalizing-- softmax
is exponential over
some exponentials--
that will cancel.
The thing that
matters is c2, and you
can approximate that nicely
with the beta coefficient that's
used in the softmax.
And so yeah, I
guess, as well, I'll
focus first on the binary
original version of SDM.
But then we also develop
a continuous version.
OK, so yeah, the two things
that you need for this circle
intersection, and
the exponential decay
to work, or to map
it to attention,
is you need some notion
of continuous space.
And so you can use this equation
here to map Hamming distances,
to discretize cosine
similarity values, where
the hats over the vectors
are L2 nominalizations.
And you can then write the
circle intersection equation
on the left as this exponential
with these two concepts
that you need to learn.
And then rewrite this
by converting c2 to c--
you can write this as
a beta coefficient.
Let me get to some plots.
Yeah, so you need the
correct coefficient.
But you can fit this with a log
linear regression in a closed
form.
I want to show a plot here.
Yeah, OK, so in the blue
is our circle intersection
for two different
Hamming distances, both
using 64 dimensional vectors.
And the orange is our actual
softmax attention operation
where we fit the beta
coefficient, such
that it will--
the Hamming distance
used by attention
is equivalent to the Hamming
distance used by SDM.
And you can see-- so the main
plot is the normalized weights,
so just summed up and
undivided, so this one,
and then I've logged plots here.
And you can see that
in not log space,
the curves agree quite nicely.
You can see that for
the higher dimensional--
sorry, the larger Hamming
distance, the log plot
you see this drop off here
where the circle intersection
stops being exponential.
But it turns out this
actually isn't a problem,
because the point
at which the drop--
the exponential breaks down,
you're at approximately 0.20
here.
And you're basically
paying negligible attention
to any of those points.
And so in the regime where the
exponential really matters,
this approximation holds true.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
Yeah, the [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah, yeah, no, I just wanted
to actually show a figure
to get some intuition before--
yeah.
So all we're doing
here is we're just--
we're in a binary space
with the original SDM,
and we're just using this
mapping to cosine similarity.
And then, what you need to do is
just have the beta coefficient
split.
And you can view
your beta coefficient
in attention as determining
how [INAUDIBLE] things
are, and this relates
directly to the Hamming
distance of your circles
that you're using for read
and write on version.
And so, yeah, it's
like mathematically
to show this now, on this
slide, I'm not using any tricks.
I'm just rewriting attention
using the SDM notation
of patterns and queries.
So this little box down
here is doing that mapping.
And this is the money slide
where we're updating our query,
and on the left, we have
our attention equation
written in SDM notation.
We expand our softmax.
And then, the main
statement is that this
is closely approximated
by if we swap out
our exponential with the SDM
circle intersection equation.
So and again, the two things
that you need for this to work
are one, your attention
vectors, your keys and queries
need to be normalized,
so I have hats on them.
And then, you want--
if you decide to give a
Hamming distance for SDM,
and I'll get into what
Hamming distances are
good for different
things, then you
need to have a beta
coefficient that relates to it.
But again, that's just
how many things are you
trying to pay attention to.
So yeah, just as
a quick side note,
you can write SDM using
continuous vectors,
and then not need this
mapping to cosine similarity.
And so here, I have the
plots again, but with this.
And I've added-- but the orange
and the green are flipped,
so I've added the continuous
approximation here, too.
And what's nice about
the continuous version
is you can actually then
write sparse distributed
memory as a multi-layer
perceptron with slightly
different assumptions.
And I'm not going to
talk about that now,
but this is featured
in Sparks III--
Memories of a Continual
Learner, which
was added to the
additional readings.
And it'll be in--
sorry, this shouldn't say
ICML, this should say ICLEAR.
It's just been accepted
to ICLEAR for this year.
OK, so do train transformers
use these beta coefficients
that I've said are
similar to those for SDM?
And so, it shouldn't
be surprising
that depending on the
Hamming distance you've set,
SDM is better for
certain things.
For example, you
just want to store
as many memories as
possible, and you're assuming
that your queries aren't noisy.
Or you're assuming your
queries are really noisy,
so you can't store
as much, but you can
retrieve from a long distance.
And if attention
of the transformer
is implementing sparse
distributed memory,
we should expect to see
that the beta coefficients
that the transformer
uses correspond
to these good instances of SDM.
And so we have some weak
evidence that that's the case.
So this is the key
query normalized variant
of attention, where you actually
learn your beta coefficient.
Normally in
transformers, you don't.
But you don't L2
norm your vectors,
and so you can kind of have
this effective beta coefficient.
So in this case, it's just
a cleaner instance where
we're actually learning beta.
And this was trained on a number
of different translation tasks.
We take the learned
beta coefficients
across layers and across tasks
and plot them as a histogram.
And the red-dotted
lines correspond
to three different notions of
sparse distributed memory that
are optimal for
different things.
And again, this is weak
evidence, insomuch as
to derive the optimal
SDM beta coefficients,
or corresponding
Hamming distances.
We need to assume
random patterns
in this high dimensional space.
And obviously, real
world data isn't random.
However, it is nice to see one,
all of the beta coefficients
fall within the bounds.
And two, they skew towards
the max query noise, which
makes more sense
if you're dealing
with complicated real world
data where the next data points
you see might be
out of distribution,
based on what you've
seen in the past.
The maxmemory capacity variant
assumes no query noise at all.
And so it's like, how
many things can I pack in,
assuming that the questions
I'm asking the system
are perfectly formed?
OK, just talking a little bit
about transformer components
more broadly.
So I've mentioned that you can
write the feedforward layer
as a version of SDM, that has
a sort of notion of longer term
memory.
There's also LayerNorm, which
is crucial in transformers.
And it's not quite
the same, but it
can be related to the
L2 normalization that's
required by SDM.
There's also the key query
normalization variant
that explicitly does
this L2 normalization.
And it does get slightly
better performance, at least
on the small tests
that they did.
I don't know if this would
scale to larger models.
And so, I guess this work
is interesting in so much as
like the biological
plausibility, which
I'm about to get to.
And then, the links
to transformers.
It hasn't, to date, improved
transformer architectures.
But that doesn't mean that this
lens couldn't be used or be
useful in some way.
So yeah, I list a
few other things
that SDM is related to that
could be used to funnel in.
And actually, in the new work
where SDM is continual learner,
we kind of expand the
cerebellar circuit,
look at components of it,
particularly inhibitory
interneurons.
Implement those in a
deep learning model,
and it then becomes much
better at continual learning.
So that was kind of a fun way of
actually using this link to get
better bottom line performance.
OK, so a summary of this
section is basically
just the intersection
between two hyperspheres
approximates an exponential.
And this allows SDM's
read and write operations
to approximate
attention, both in theory
and our limited tests.
And so kind of like big
picture research questions
that could come out of this is,
first, is the transformer so
successful because it's
performing some key cognitive
operation?
The cerebellum is a
very old brain region
used by most organisms,
including fruit flies, maybe
even cephalopods, through like
divergent, but now convergent
evolution.
And then, given that
the transformer has
been so successful
empirically, is SDM actually
the correct theory for
cerebellar function?
And that's still
an open question.
As we learn more and more
about the cerebellum,
there's nothing that yet
disproves SDM as working there.
And I think it's--
I'll go out on a
limb, and say it's
like one of the more compelling
theories for how the cerebellum
is actually working.
Yeah, and so I think this
work kind of motivates looking
more of these questions--
both of these questions
more seriously.
Do we have time?
Cool.
So here's the circuit
that implements SDM.
At the bottom, we have patterns
coming in for either reading
or writing.
And they're going to actually
break down into these slides.
OK, yeah, so first, we
have patterns that come in.
And every neuron
here-- these are
the dendrites of each neuron.
And they're deciding
whether or not
they're going to fire for
the input that comes in.
Then, if the neuron
does fire, and you're
writing in that pattern,
then you simultaneously--
and I'm going to
explain this to you,
you're going to be
like this is crazy,
the brain doesn't do this.
And then, I'm going to
hopefully show you it does.
You not only need to have
the thing the pattern
that activates
neurons, but you need
to have a separate line that
tells the neuron what to store.
And just like you have this
difference between keys
and values, where they can be
different vectors representing
different things,
here, you can have
a key that comes in and tells
the neuron when to activate.
And the value for what
it should actually
store, and [INAUDIBLE].
This is called hetero
associative mapping.
And then, once you're
reading from the system,
you also have your query come
in here, activate neurons,
and those neurons then
output whatever they stored.
And the neurons vector
is this particular column
that it's stored.
And it's, as a
reminder, it's storing
patterns in superposition.
And then, it will dump whatever
it stored across these output
lines.
And then, you have this
G majority bit operation
to convert to a 0 or 1, decide
if the neuron is going to fire
or not.
And so, here is
the same circuit,
but where I overlay cell
types in the cerebellum.
And so I'll come
back to this slide,
because most people probably
aren't familiar with cerebellar
circuitry.
Let me just-- it's in water.
OK, so the way
that the cerebellum
is pretty homogeneous,
in that it follows
this pattern throughout.
Also fun fact, 70% of
all neurons in the brain
are in the cerebellum.
They're small, so
you wouldn't know it,
but the cerebellum is
very underappreciated,
and there's a bunch
of evidence that it
has closed loop systems with
most higher order cognitive
processing now.
If your cerebellum
is damaged, you
are more likely to have
autism, et cetera, et cetera.
So it does a lot more than
just fine motor coordination.
Which a lot of people
have assumed in the past.
OK, so inputs come in through
the muscle fibers here.
They interface
with granule cells.
This is a major up
projection, where you have
tons and tons of granule cells.
Each granule cell has what are
called parallel fibers, which
are incredibly long
and thin axons that
branch out in this T-structure.
And then, they're hit
by the purkinje cells,
which will receive up to
100,000 parallel fiber inputs.
It's the highest connectivity
of any neuron in the brain.
And then, the purkinje cell will
decide whether or not to fire,
and send its output
downwards here.
So that's the whole system
where patterns come in
and the neurons decide
if they fire or not.
And the way that they
then output their output.
You then have a
separate right line,
which is the climbing biopsy.
So the climbing fibers
come up, and they're
pretty amazing in that
these connections here, you
kind of know are
not as important.
The one that really matters is
that they're not very strong,
either.
Or what really
matters is it goes up
and it wraps around
individual purkinje cells.
And the mapping is
close to one to one,
between climbing fibers
and purkinje cells.
And leads to very strong
action potentials.
They're connecting to us here?
In these--
Yes, in the stuff
off to the side?
Yeah, right, these two lines.
They're [INAUDIBLE].
Oh, so they're separate neurons
coming from separate areas.
Purkinje cells go into
deep cerebellar nuclei,
kind of in the core
of the cerebellum.
And that then feeds
into thalamus,
like back to high
order brain regions,
or like down the muscle
movement, et cetera.
A lot of people will think
of the cerebellum as kind
of like a fine-tuning lookup
table, where you've already
decided the muscle
movement you want to do,
but the cerebellum will then
do a bunch of adjustments.
So that it's much more accurate.
But it seems like
this also applies
to next word prediction.
Like we have fMRI data for this.
A neuroscientist once said to
me that a dirty little secret
of fMRI is that the cerebellum
lights up for everything.
So OK, going back to
this circuit here, then.
Yeah--
Timescales, are these
operating again?
I mean, how long
is the information
stored and retrieved?
Do we have any idea about this?
Like it's just like a
couple of milliseconds,
or is this information
more persistent?
So the main theory
is that you have
updating through time-dependent
plasticity, where your climbing
fiber will either-- which is
doing what you want right then,
will fire either just before or
just after your granule cells
fire.
And so that, then,
updates the purkinje cell
synapses for long term
depression or potentiation.
So whatever timescale
that's happening on.
The climbing fiber makes very
large vector potentials--
or it leads to very large vector
potentials within the cell.
And so I do think you could get
pretty fast synaptic updates.
And they're also
persistent for a long time?
I think so, yeah.
The synapses are steady for
like the rest of your life?
Yeah, yeah.
So what's really unique
about this circuit
is the fact that you have these
two orthogonal inputs, where
you have the mossy fibers
bringing information.
And then it's decided if the
neurons are going to fire
or not.
But then the totally
separate fiber lines
that can update
specific neurons,
and what they're storing
and will later output.
And then, the purkinje
cell is so important,
it's kind of doing this pooling
across every single neuron.
And each neuron, remember,
it's storing a vector this way.
And so the purkinje cell is
doing element wise, summation,
and then deciding
whether it fires or not.
And this allows for you to store
your vectors in superposition,
and then later denoise them.
The theory [INAUDIBLE]
maps quite well
to the Marr and Albus theories
of cerebellar function, which
are still quite dominant,
if anyone's familiar
and wants to dive
deep into those.
Yeah?
So the analogy of the neuron
in SDM you introduced before,
was that basically each
neuron in purkinje cell?
In this setting?
Each neuron is a granule cell.
And then, yeah, so the
location of the neuron,
those hollow circles,
corresponds to the granule cell
dendrites here, where
the patterns that pop in
correspond to the activations
of the muscle fibers.
And then, the afferent
postsynaptic connections
are with the purkinje cell.
So that's actually
what it's storing
is in the synaptic
connections with the--
and purkinje cells
at that interface.
And then, the purkinje
cell does the majority
of the operation in deciding
if it wants to fire or not.
Got about five minutes.
Can we ask you questions?
Yeah, yeah, I think we're
basically into question time.
So yeah, thanks a lot.
So I have a question.
I don't know anything
about SDM, but it
seems, as understood, it's
very good for long-term memory.
And I have a question--
what's your hypothesis of what
we should be doing
for short-term memory.
Because it seems that--
so if you have this
link of transformers
having long-term memory, what's
good for short-term memory?
Because for me, it
seems like we are
doing this in the prompt
context right now.
But how could we incorporate
these two together?
Yeah, so this work
actually focuses more
on the short-term memory.
Where it relates to the
attention operation.
But you can rewrite SDM.
It's almost more natural to
interpret it as a multi-layer
perceptron, that does like a
softmax activation across--
or a top-K activation
across its neurons.
It's like a little bit
more complicated than that.
But yeah, so the--
yeah, the most
interesting thing here
is the fact that I just
have a bunch of neurons,
and inactivating nearby neurons
in this high dimensional space,
you get this
exponential weighting,
which is the softmax.
And then, because it's an
associative memory where
you have keys and
values, it is attention.
And yeah, I guess like
the thing I most want
to drive home from this is
like it's actually surprisingly
easy for the brain to implement
the attention operation,
the attention equation.
Just using
high-dimensional vectors,
and activating your mappings.
So it's good for short term?
Yes, if you were actually
used SDM for attention,
yeah-- so let me go all
the way back real quick.
This is important.
There are two ways of
SDM, and I don't think
you were here for the talk.
I think I saw you come in a bit
later, which is totally fine.
I was listening, but
didn't get this part.
Oh, cool, cool, cool.
Yeah, OK, so there are two
ways of looking at SDM.
There's the neuron perspective,
which is this one here.
And this is actually
what's going
on in the brain, of course.
And so the only thing
that is actually constant
is the neurons, the
patterns are ephemeral.
And then, there's the
pattern-based perspective,
which is actually what
attention is doing.
And so here, you're
abstracting away the neurons,
or assuming they're
operating under the hood.
But what you're
actually computing
is the distance between
the true location
of your pattern [INAUDIBLE].
And there are pros and
cons to both of these.
The pro to this is you get much
higher fidelity distances--
like you know exactly
how far the query is
from the original patterns.
And that's really
important when you're
deciding what to update for.
It's like you really want
to know what is closest
and what is further away,
and be able to apply
the exponential
weighting correctly.
The problem is, you need to
store all of your pattern
locations in memory.
And so this is why transformers
have limited context windows.
The other perspective is this
long-term memory one, where
you forget about the patterns.
And you just look
at where you just
have your neurons that store
a bunch of patterns in them,
in this noisy superposition.
And so you can't really--
you can triangulate the
original pattern, but not quite.
And it's all much noisier.
But you can store
tons of patterns
and you're not constrained
by a context window.
You can think of any
MLP layer as storing
like the entire data set in a
noisy superposition of states.
Yeah, hopefully that kind
of answers your question.
I think there's one here first.
Yeah?
So I guess my question is like--
so I guess like you
kind of have shown
that like modern
self-attention mechanism maps
onto this SDM mechanism, that
like seems possible in some
of the modern contemporary
theories of common brain coule
implement SDM.
And I guess my question
is, to what degree has that
been experimentally verified?
Versus you were mentioning
earlier that it might actually
be easier to have
done this using
an MLP layer, in some sense,
than like [INAUDIBLE]..
And so how do
experimentalists actually
distinguish between
competing hypotheses?
Like for instance,
one thing that I
wasn't entirely clear
about is even if the brain
could do attention, or SDM, that
doesn't actually mean it would,
because maybe it
can't do [INAUDIBLE]..
So like how do you--
how does this get
actually tested?
Totally, yeah.
So on the backprop
point, you wouldn't
have to do it here because you
have the climbing fibers that
can directly give
training signals to what
the neuron should store.
So in this case, it's like a
supervised learning task where
the climbing fiber knows
what it wants to write in,
or how it should be updated,
the purkinje cell synapses.
But for your broader point, you
basically need to test this,
you need to be able to
do real time learning.
The Drosophila mushroom
body is basically
identical to the cerebellum, and
the fly and the brain data set
has done most of the
individual neuron connectivity.
But what you would
really want to do
is like in vitro,
real time, super--
super, super high frames
per second calcium imaging.
And be able to see how
synapses change over time.
And so for an associative
learning task,
hear a sound move left, hear
another sound move right,
or smells, or whatever.
Present one of those, trace--
figure out the small
subset of neurons
that fire, which we
know is a small subset.
So that already fits
with the interpretation.
See how the synapses
here update,
and how the outputs
of that correspond
to changes in motor action.
And then, extinguish
that memory.
So write in a new one, and
then watch it go away again.
And our cameras are
getting fast enough,
and our calcium and
voltage indicators
are getting to be really good.
So hopefully in the
next three to five years
we can do some of those tasks.
But I think that would
be very definitive.
Yeah.
Yeah, do we have
any other questions?
I think there one more,
and then I should--
How you map the neuron in SDM,
like this final hypothetical
biological
implementation, what is
the range of your circle
that you're mapping around?
Is that like the [INAUDIBLE]?
I was trying to understand
how that [INAUDIBLE]..
Yeah, so I wouldn't get
confused with multi-headedness,
because that's different
attention heads all doing
their own attention operation.
It's funny, though, the
cerebellum has microzones,
which you can think of as
like separate attention
heads in a way.
I don't want to take
that analogy too far,
but it is somewhat interesting.
So the way you relate
this is in attention,
you have your beta coefficient.
That is an effective
beta coefficient
because the vector norms
of your keys and queries
aren't constrained.
That corresponds to
a Hamming distance.
And here, that corresponds
to the number of neurons that
are on for any given input.
And the Hamming
distance you want,
I had that the slide before,
the Hamming distance you want
depends upon what you're
actually trying to do.
And if you're not trying to
store that many memories,
for example, you can have
a higher Hamming distance,
because you can get
a higher fidelity
calculation for the
number of neurons
in that noisy intersection.
Yeah.
Cool, yeah, thanks a lot.
[INAUDIBLE]
So as a disclaimer,
so as a disclaimer
before I introduce
our next speaker,
the person who was
scheduled unfortunately
had to cancel last
minute due to faculty.
Interviews so our next
speaker has very graciously
agreed to present
at very last minute,
but we are very grateful to him.
So I'd like to introduce
everybody to Will.
So Will is a computational
neuroscience machine
learning PhD student at
the University College
London at their Gatsby unit.
So I don't know if anybody
has heard about the Gatsby a--
I'm a bit of a history
buff, or a history
nerd, depending on
how you phrase it.
The Gatsby unit was actually
this incredible powerhouse
in the 1990s and 2000s.
So Hinton used to be there,
Zoubin Ghahramani used
to be there.
He's now in charge
of Google research.
I think they've done a
tremendous amount of good work.
Anyways, and now,
I'd like to invite
Will to talk about how
to build a cognitive map.
Did you want to
share your screen?
Yeah.
OK, can you stand
in front of here?
Let me stop sharing.
OK, so I'm going to be
presenting this work.
It's all about how a model
that people in the group
that I work with, to study the
hippocampal entorhinal system,
completely
independently turned out
to look a bit like
a transformer.
So that's this paper
that I'm going to talk
about is describing that link.
And so the paper
that builds this link
is by these three people.
James is a postdoc
half at Stanford.
Tim is a professor at
Oxford and in London.
And Joe's a PhD
student in London.
So three of them.
So this is the problem
that this model
of the hippocampal
entorhinal system,
which we'll talk more
about, is supposed to solve.
It's basically the
observation there's
a lot of structure in the
world, and generally, we
should use it in order
to generalize quickly
between tasks.
So the kind of thing
I mean by that is you
know 2D space works, because
of your long experience
living in the world.
And so if you start at this
greenhouse, and step north,
this orange one, then to this
red one, then this pink one,
because of the
structure of 2D space,
you can think to
yourself, oh, what
will happen if I step left?
And you know that you'll end
up back at the green one,
because loops of this
type close in 2D space.
And this is-- perhaps patterns
is a new city you've just
arrived in.
This is like a zero
shot generalization,
because you somehow realized
that the structure applies
more broadly and use
it in a new context.
Yeah, and there's
generally a lot
of these kinds of situations
where there structures
reappear in the world.
So there can be
lots of instances
where the same structure will be
useful to doing these zero shot
generalizations to predict
what you're going to see next.
And so, you might be able
to see how we're already
going to start mapping this
onto some kind of sequence
prediction task that feels a
bit transformer-esque, which
is, you receive this
sequence of observations,
and in this case, actions,
movements in space.
And your job is, given a
new action, step left here,
you have to try and predict
what you're going to see.
So that's the kind of sequence
prediction version of it.
And the way we're going
to try and solve this
is based on factorization.
It's like, you can't
go into one environment
and just learn from the
experiences in that one
environment, you
have to separate out
the structure and
the experiences
you're having, so that you
can reuse the structural part,
which appears very
often in the world.
And so separating
memories from structure.
And so, you know, here's
our separation of the two.
We have our dude wandering
around this like 2D grid world.
And you want to separate out
the fact that there's 2D space,
and it's 2D space that has
these rules underlying it.
And in a particular instance, in
the environment that you're in,
you need to be able to recall
which objects are at which
locations in the environment.
So in this case, it's
like oh, this position
has an orange house,
this position--
that's green, sorry,
orange, red, and pink.
And so you have
to bind those two,
you have to be like, whenever
you realize that you're back
in this position, recall that
is the observation you're
going to see there.
And so this model that
we're going to build
is some model that
tries to achieve this.
New task-- and so
when you enter it,
imagine you enter
a new environment
with the same structure, you
wander around and realize
it's the same structure.
All you have to do is
bind the new things
that you see to the locations,
and then you're done.
Task done.
You know how the world works.
So this is what neuroscientists
mean by a cognitive map,
is this idea of separating
out and understanding
the structure that you can
reuse in new situations.
And yeah, this model that
was built in the lab,
is a model of this
process happening,
of this separation
between the two of them
and how you use them
to do new inferences.
And this is the
bit that's supposed
looked like a transformer.
So that's a general
introduction,
and then we'll dive into
it a little more now.
Makes sense, though,
the broad picture?
Good, silence I'll
assume is good.
So we'll start off
with some brain stuff.
So there's a long
stream of evidence
from spatial navigation
that the brain
is doing something like this.
I mean, I think you can probably
imagine how you, yourself, are
doing this already when
you go to a new city,
or you're like
trying to understand
a new task that has some
structure that you recognize
from previously.
You can see how
this is something
that you're probably doing.
But spatial navigation is
an area in neuroscience
which had like a huge stream
of discoveries over the last 50
years.
And a lot of evidence
of the neural basis
of this computation.
So we're going to talk through
some of those examples.
The earliest of these,
psychologists like Tolman,
who were showing that
rats, in this case,
can do this kind of path
integration of structure.
So the way this work is they
got put at a start position
here, down at the bottom
S, and they got trained
that this route up
here got your reward.
So this is the maze
they had to run around.
Then they were asked--
they were put in this new--
the same thing, but
they blocked off
this path that takes
this long, winding route,
and given instead a selection
of all these arms to go down.
And they look at which
path the rat goes down.
And the finding is
that the rat goes down
the one that corresponds to
heading off in this direction.
So the rat has somehow
not just learned--
one option of this is like
blind memorization of actions
that I need to take in
order to route around.
Instead, no, it's
learning actually
that embedding the reward and
its understanding of 2D space,
and taking the direct route
there even though it's never
taken it before.
So there's evidence that rats
are doing this as well as us.
And then, a series
of neural discoveries
about the basis of this,
so John O'Keefe stuck
an electrode in the hippocampus,
which is a brain area we'll
talk more about, and found
these things called place cells.
So what I'm plotting
here is each
of these columns
is a single neuron,
and the mouse or rat,
I can't remember,
is running around a
square environment.
The black lines are the path the
rodent traces out through time,
and you put a red dot
down every time you see
this individual neuron spike.
And then, the
bottom plot of this
is just a smooth
version of that spike.
So that firing rate.
Which you can think of as
like the activity of a neuron
and neural network.
That's the analogy that
people usually draw.
And so these ones are
called place cells,
because they're
neurons that respond
in a particular
position in space.
And in the '70s, this
was huge excitement.
People had been studying mainly
like sensory systems and motor
output.
And suddenly, a deep
cognitive variable
place, something you never--
you don't have a signaler,
but somehow there's
this signal for what
looks like position in the brain
in very understandable ways.
The next step in--
the biggest step, I guess,
in this chain of discovery,
is the Moser lab which
is a group in Norway,
they stuck an electron in a
different area of the brain,
the medial entorhinal cortex.
And so this is the
hippocampal entorhinal system
we're going to be talking about.
And they found this
neuron called a grid cell.
So again, the same
plot structure
that I'm showing here,
but instead, these neurons
respond not in one
position in a room,
but at a hexagonal lattice
of positions in a room.
So these two, I guess I'm
showing to you, because they
really motivate the underlying
neural basis of this kind
of spatial cognition,
embodying the structure
of this space in some way.
That's a very
surprising finding,
why are neurons choosing
to represent things
with this hexagonal lattice?
It's like yeah, provoked
a lot of research since.
And broadly, there's been many
more discoveries in this area.
So there's place cells
I've talked to you
about, grid cells,
cells that respond based
on the location of not yourself
but another animal, cells that
respond when your head is facing
a particular direction, cells
that respond to when you're
a particular distance away
from an object.
So like I'm one step south of
an object, that kind of cell.
Cells that respond
to a reward position.
Cells respond to
vectors, to boundaries,
cells respond to
[INAUDIBLE],, so there's
like all sorts, all
kinds of structure
that this pair of
brain structures,
the hippocampus
here, this red area,
and the entorhinal cortex
this blue area here, which
is conserved across-- a lot
of species are represented.
There's also finally one
finding in this that's fun,
is they did an fMRI experiment
on London taxi cab drivers.
And I don't know
if you know this,
but the London
taxicab drivers, they
do a thing called
the knowledge, which
is a two-year long test
where they have to learn
every street in London.
And the idea is, the
tests go something like,
oh, there's a traffic jam
here, and a roadwork here,
and I need to get from like
Camden Town down to Wandsworth
in the quickest way possible.
What route would you go?
And they have to
tell you which route
they're going be able to
take through all the roads,
and how they would
re-plan if they found
a stop-- those kind of things.
So it's like
intense, you see them
like driving around sometimes
learning all of these routes
with little maps.
They're being made a little
bit obsolete by Google Maps,
but you know, luckily
they got them before--
this experiment was done
before that was true.
And so they've got
here is a measure
of the size of your
hippocampus using
fMRI, versus how long
you've been a taxi cab
driver in months.
And the claim is basically
the longer you're a taxi cab
driver, the bigger
your hippocampus,
because the more
you're having to do
this kind of spatial reasoning.
So that's a big set of
evidence that these brain areas
are doing something
to do with space.
But there's a lot of evidence
that there's something more
than that, something non-spatial
going on in these areas.
And we're going to
build these together
to make the broader claim about
this underlying structural
inference.
And so I'm going to talk
through a couple of those.
The first one of these is
a guy called patient HM--
this is the most studied
patient in medical history.
He had epilepsy, and to
cure intractable epilepsy,
you have to cut out
the brain region that's
causing these seizure-like
events in your brain.
And in this case, the
epilepsy was coming
from the guy's hippocampus.
So they bilaterally
lesioned his hippocampus--
they cut out both
of his hippocampi.
And it turned out that this
guy then had terrible amnesia.
He never formed
another memory again.
And he could only recall
memories from a long time
before the surgery happened.
But yeah, so experiments
showed a lot of this stuff
about how we understand
the neural basis of memory.
Things like he could
learn to do motor tasks--
so somehow the motor tasks
are being [INAUDIBLE]..
For example, they gave him
some very difficult motor
coordination tasks that people
can't generally do, but can
with a lot of practice, and
he got very good at this.
Eventually, and was as
good as other people
at learning to do that, he had
no recollection of ever doing
the task.
So he'd go into the
do this new task,
and be like, I've
never seen this before.
I have no idea what
you're asking me to do.
And you do it amazingly.
And be like-- yeah.
So there's some evidence
there that the hippocampus
is involved in at least
some parts of memory, which
seems a bit separate to
this stuff about space
that I've been
talking to you about.
The second of these
is imagining things.
So this is actually a
paper by Demis Hassabis,
who, before he was DeepMind
head, was a neuroscientist.
And here, maybe you
can't read that, I'll
read some of these out.
You're asked to imagine you're
lying on a white sandy beach
in a beautiful tropical bay.
And so the control, this
bottom one says things like,
it's very hot, and the
sun is beating down on me,
the sand underneath me
is almost unbearably hot.
I can hear the sounds of small
wavelets lapping on the beach.
The sea is gorgeous,
aquamarine color.
You know, like so a
nice, lucid description
of this beachy scene.
Whereas the person with a
hippocampal damage says,
as for seeing, I can't really,
apart from just the sky.
I can hear the sound of
seagulls, and of the sea.
I could feel the grain of
sand beneath my fingers.
And then, like yeah,
struggles, basically.
Really struggles to do
this, imagine this scenario.
Some of the things really
are very surprising.
So the last of these is this
transitive inference task.
So transitive
inference-- A is greater
than B, B is greater than C,
therefore, A is greater than C.
And the way they convert this
into a rodent experiment,
is you get given two
pots of food that
have different smells.
And your job is to go
to the pot of food--
you learn which pot
of food has-- sorry,
which pot with the
smell has the food.
And so these are colored by
the two pots by their smell.
And the rodent has to learn
to go to a particular pot,
in this case, the one
that smells like A.
And they do two of these.
They do A has the food when
it's presented in a pair with B,
and B has the food when it's
presented in a pair with C.
And then they test,
what does a mouse do
when presented with A and C
in a completely new situation?
And if they have a
hippocampus, they'll
go for A over C. They'll
do transitive inference.
If they don't have
one, they can't.
And so, there's a
much more broad--
this is like oh, I've
shown you how hippocampus
is used for this spatial
stuff, that people
have been excited about.
But there's also all of this
kind of relational stuff,
imagining new situations, some
slightly more complex story
here.
The last of these
I'm going to do
is how the entorhinal
cortex, as well.
So that's where, if you remember
hippocampus was these guys,
and cortex was these
grid cells, was
how entorhinal cortex was
appearing to do some broader
stuff, as well.
This is all motivation
for the model.
We're just trying to build
all of these things together.
So in this one, this is called
the stretchy birds' task.
So you put people
in an fMRI machine,
and you make them navigate,
but navigate in bird space.
And what bird
space means is it's
a two-dimensional
space of images.
And each image is
one of these birds.
And as you vary along
the x dimension,
the birds legs get
longer and shorter.
And as you vary along
the y direction,
the bird's neck gets
longer and shorter.
And the patients sit there,
or subjects sit there,
and just watch the
bird images change,
so that it traces out
some path in 2D space.
But they never see the 2D space.
They just see the images.
And the claim is
basically-- and then
they're asked to do
some navigational tasks.
They're like, oh,
whenever you're
in this place in
2D space, you show
Santa Claus next to the bird.
And so the participants have
to pin that particular bird
image, that particular place
in 2D space to the Santa Claus.
And you're asked to go and
find the Santa Claus again,
using some non-directional
controller.
And they navigate
their way back.
And the claim is that these
people use grid cells.
So the entorhinal
cortex is active in how
these people are navigating this
abstract cognitive bird space.
And the way you test
that claim is you
look at the fMRI signal
in the entorhinal cortex
as the participants head at some
particular angle in bird space.
And because of the
six-fold symmetry
of the hexagonal lattice, you
get this six-fold symmetric
waving up and down of the
entorhinal cortex activity
as you head in particular
directions in 2D space.
There's evidence
that this system
is being used not just for
navigation in 2D space,
but any cognitive task with
some underlying structure
that you can extract.
You use it to do these tasks.
Is there significance to bird
space also being to here?
Yes, yes.
Like people try this
with multiple dimensions
variability?
People haven't done
that experiment.
But people have done things
like look at how grid cells--
have they even done that.
They've done things
like 3D space,
but not like cognitive 3D space.
They've done like literally like
make-- they've done it in bats,
they stick electrodes in bats
and make the bats fly around
the room and look at how
the grid cells respond.
Yeah, but definitely, I
think they've done it--
ah, they've done it
in sequence space.
So in this case,
you hear a sequence
of sounds with
hierarchical structure.
So it's like how there's
months, weeks, days,
and meals, something like that.
So like weeks have a
periodic structure,
months have a
days have a periodic
structure, and meals
have a periodic structure.
And so you hear a
sequence of sounds
with exactly the same
kind of structure
as that hierarchy of sequences.
And you look at
the representation
in the entorhinal
cortex through fMRI.
And you see exactly
the same thing--
that the structure is all
represented like that.
Even more than
that, you actually
see in the entorhinal cortex
a array of length scales.
So at one end of the
entorhinal cortex,
you've got very large
length scale grid
cells that are like responding
to large variations in space.
The other end, you've
got very small ones,
and you see the same
thing recapitulated there.
The meals cycle, that
cycles a lot more quicker,
is represented in one end of
the entorhinal cortex and fMRI,
and the month cycle
is at the other end,
with a [INAUDIBLE]
scale in between.
So there's some
evidence to that end.
All right, so I've
been talking about MEC,
the medial entorhinal cortex.
Another brain area that
people don't look at it
as much is the LEC, the
laterl entorhinal cortex,
that will then be
important for this model.
And basically, the
only that you should
be aware of before
we get to the model,
is that it seems to represent
very high level the similarity
structure in the lateral cortex.
Seems to be a very high
level semantic one.
For example, you
present some images,
and you look at how the
visual cortex, things are more
similarly represented
if they look similar.
But by the time you get to
the lateral entorhinal cortex,
things look more similar
based on their usage.
For example, like an
ironing board and an iron
will be represented similarly.
Even though they
look very different,
because they are somehow
like semantically linked.
OK, so that's the
role that the LEC
is going to play in this model.
So yeah, basically,
the claim is this
is for more than just 2D space.
So the neural implementation
of this cognitive map,
which is for not only 2D space,
which this cartoon is supposed
to represent, but also
things any other structure.
So some structures like
transitive inference, this one
is faster than that
and faster than that.
Or family trees, like this
person's my mother's brother,
and is therefore my uncle,
those kind of things.
These broader
structural inferences
that you want to be able
to use in many situations,
so it's basically
the same problem.
Great, that was a
load of neuroscience.
And now we're going to
get on to the model that
tries to summarize
all of these things.
And that's going to be
the model that will end up
looking like a transformer.
So yeah, we basically
want the separation.
These diagrams here are
supposed to represent
a particular environment
that you're wandering around.
It has an underlying
grid structure,
and you see a set of
stimuli at each point
on these grid, which are
these little cartoon things.
And you want to try and create
a thing that separates out
this like 2D structural grid
from the actual experiences
you're seeing.
And then mapping
to the things I've
been showing you is
that this grid like code
is actually the grid cells, and
the medial entorhinal cortex,
are somehow abstracting
the structure.
The lateral entorhinal cortex,
encoding these semantically
meaningful similarities, will be
the objects that you're seeing.
So it's just like this is
what I'm seeing in the world.
And the combination
of the two of them
will be the hippocampus.
So yeah, in more
diagrams we've got
G, the structural code, the
grid code, and MEC, the LEC--
is someone asking a question?
Since morning, so
now it's lunchtime.
Yeah.
Sorry, I can't hear you, if
you're asking a question.
How do I mute
someone if they're--
Maybe type it in the
chat if there is one.
Nice.
So yeah, we got the
hippocampus in the middle,
which is going to be our binding
of the two of them together.
So I'm going to step through
each of these three parts
on their own, and
how they do the job
that I've assigned to them.
And then, come back together
and show the full model.
So lateral entorhinal cortex
encodes what you're seeing.
So this is like these
images, or the houses
we were looking at before.
And that would just be some
vector XT that's different.
So a random vector,
different for every signal.
The medial entorhinal cortex
is the one that tells you
where you are in space.
And it has the job
of path-integrating.
So this means receiving
a sequence of actions
that you've taken in space,
for example, went north, east,
and south, and telling you
where in 2D space that you are.
So somehow the bit that embeds
the structure of the world.
And the way that we'll
do that is this g of T,
this vector of activities
in this brain area,
will be updated by a
matrix that depends
on the actions you've taken.
OK, so if you step north,
you update the representation
with the step north matrix.
And those matrices are going
to have to obey some rules.
For example, if you step
north and step south,
you haven't moved, and
so the step north matrix,
the step south matrix, have
to be inverses of one another.
So that the activity
stays the same
and represents the structure
of the world somehow.
OK, so that's the
world structure part.
Finally, the memory,
because we have
to memorize which things we
found at which positions,
going to happen in
the hippocampus,
and that's going to be through
a version of these things
called the Hopfield
networks, that you heard
mentioned in the last talk.
So this is like a content
addressable memory,
and it's biologically
plausible, this claim.
The way it works is you
have a set of activities, p,
which are the activities
of all these neurons.
And when it receives--
and it just like
recurrently updates itself.
So there's some weight
matrix in here, w--
and some non-linearity, and
you roll it forward in time.
And it just settles into
this dynamical system.
It settles into some
attractor state.
And the way you
make it do memory
is through the weight matrix.
So you make it like a sum of
outer products of these pi mu,
each chi is some
memory, some pattern
that you want to recall.
And then, this is just
writing it in there.
The update pattern is like that.
And the claim is basically
that if p, the memory--
the activity of the neurons,
the hippocampal neurons,
is close to some
memory, say chi mu,
then this dot product
will be much larger
than all of the
other dot products
with all the other memories.
So the sum over all
of them will basically
be dominated by this
one term, chi mu.
And so your
attractor set network
will basically settle
into that one chi mu.
And maybe the preemption sum,
that kind of comes later,
you can see how this
similarity between points is--
yeah, pairwise similarity.
And then adding
some-- adding them up,
weighted by this
similarity is the bit
that's going to turn out
looking a bit like attention.
And so some of the cool things
you can do with these systems
is like here's a set of
images that someone's
encoded in a Hopfield network.
And then someone's presented
this image to the network,
and asked it to just run to
it's like dynamical attractor
minima, and it recreates
all of the memory
that it's got stored there.
So like completes the
rest of the image.
So that's our system.
Yeah?
I'm sorry if I'm [INAUDIBLE],,
that's like where the--
[INAUDIBLE]
I've heard that
this interpretation
is like the modern
interpretation of a Hopfield
network?
This one is actually--
which interpretation, sorry?
That like it's
effectively [INAUDIBLE]..
Is that a [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah, it's only the
link to transformers
will basically only
be through the fact.
There's classic
Hopfield networks,
and then there's modern ones
that were invented like 2016.
And the link between
attention and modern
is precise the link with like
classic is not as precise.
Yeah, I mean-- yeah.
That's why I was suspecting--
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
The modern Hopfield network
is the continuous version of
[INAUDIBLE].
With the change in the
non-linearity, yeah?
Because then you have to do
the exponentiation thing.
When we get to this
later, you can tell me--
I'm sorry.
I don't mean to rail off.
No, no, more questions are good.
We'll get-- yeah.
Maybe separate energy function.
And I think the exponential
is in that, [INAUDIBLE]..
OK, thanks.
No worries.
So that's basically how our
system is going to work.
But this
Tolman-Eichenbaum machine,
that's what the name of
this thing is, and so you--
the patterns you want to
store in the hippocampus, so
these memories that
we want to embed,
are a combination of the
position and the input.
And like half of
Homer's face here,
if you then have
decided you're going
to end up at a
particular position,
you can recall the stimulus
that you saw there, and predict
that as your next observation.
Or vice versa.
If you like see a new thing,
you can infer, oh, I [INAUDIBLE]
wrong, I must actually be here.
Assuming there's usually
more than one thing
in the world that might
be in different position.
Yeah, that's the whole system.
Does the whole
Tolman-Eichenbaum machine
make sense, roughly,
what it's doing?
OK, cool.
And basically, this last bit
is saying it's really good.
So what I'm showing here, this
is on the 2D navigation task,
and so it's a big grid.
I think they use like, I don't
know, 11 by 11, or something.
And it's like wandering
around, and have
to predict what it's going to
see in some new environment.
And on here, this is the
number of nodes in that graph
that you've visited.
And on the y-axis is how
much you correctly predict.
And each of these
lines is based on how
many of those type
of environments
I've seen before, how
quickly do I learn?
And the basic
phenomenon it's showing
is, over time, as you see more
and more of these environments,
you learn to learn.
So you learn the structure
of the world, and eventually,
able to quickly generalize
to the new situation
and predict what
you're going to see.
And this scales not
with the number of edges
that you've visited, which would
be the learn-everything option.
You know, predict--
because if you're
trying to predict
which state I'm
going to see given my
current state and action,
and in a dumb way,
you just need to see
all states and
action, so all edges.
But this thing is able to do it
much more cleverly because it
only needs to visit all
nodes, and just memorize
what is at each position.
And you can see
that its learning
curve follows the number of
nodes visited learning curve.
So it's doing well.
For neuroscience, this
is also exciting is
that the neural patterns of
response in these modal regions
match the ones
observed in the brain.
So in the hippocampal
section, you
get place cell-like
activities-- this hexagon
is the grid of the environment
that it's exploring.
And plotted is the firing
rate of that neuron.
Whereas, the ones in the
medial entorhinal cortex
show this grid-like
firing pattern.
Yeah?
This exactly compare operates
on discrete spaces, essentially?
Do you have any thoughts
about how that transfers
into real world things?
We think that we'll just like
map representations into a very
nicely discretizable space?
Or do you think [INAUDIBLE]
more complicated going on?
Yeah, I imagine there's
something more complicated
going on.
I guess this--
And so it's like a super high--
No, no, no, yeah,
maybe you can make--
maybe you can make arguments
that they, as I was saying,
there's these
different modules that
operate at different scales.
You can see this already here,
like grid cells at one scale,
grid cells at another scale.
And so you could imagine how
that could be useful for-- one
of them operates at the
highest level, mixed--
one of them operates
at the lowest level,
and like adaptable.
They seem to scale up or down
depending on your environment.
And so like an adaptable
set of length scales
that you can use
to do prediction.
But that's quite speculative.
So-- OK, sorry.
Yeah?
So make sure I understand
if, you go up--
OK, one more?
Yeah, so you have your--
what's the key and
what's the value?
Yeah, so the--
And Hopfield networks
are always auto instead
of petro-associated,
so how are you--
The memories that
we're going to put in,
so the patterns,
let's say, chi mu,
is going to be some outer
product of the position
at a given time.
And the flattened-- so
yeah, take the outer product
of those, so every element in
x gets the every element of g.
Front nose out, and that's your
vector that goes [INAUDIBLE]..
Does that makes sense?
Yeah.
Sorry, I should
have put that on.
Yeah, and then you do
the same operation,
except you flatten with an
identity in the-- let's say
you're at a position you
want to print what you see.
You set x to the identity,
you do this operation,
it creates a very
big vector from g.
You put that in, and you
let it run its dynamics,
and it recalls the pattern.
And you learn a network
that like traces
out the x from that.
And the figures you show,
if you go down a bit,
it's hard to see, but what's
on the x-axis and what's--
like what-- are you training
a Hopfield network with this
flattened outer product of the--
OK.
Yeah, the actual
training that's going on
is more in the
structure of the world.
Because it has to
learn those matrices.
All it gets told is which
action type it's taking,
and it has to learn the
fact that stepping east
is the opposite
of stepping west.
So a lot of the
learning of stuff
is in those matrices, learning
to get the right structure.
There's also-- I mean, because
the Hopfield network learning,
the Hopfield network is
like re-initialize every
environment.
And you're just
shoving memories in.
So it's less like-- that's less
the bit that's-- it's causing
this, certainly, but it's
not causing this shift up.
Which is as training progresses
in many different environments,
you get better at the task.
Because it's learning the
structure of the task.
OK.
And the link to--
and this is all just
modern Hopfield networks?
The initial paper was actually
classic Hopfield networks.
But yeah, now the
new versions of it
are modern Hopfield
networks, yeah.
Right, and then, insomuch
as modern Hopfield networks
equal attention--
Is it a trap?
Yeah.
But then, you're--
OK, and then you have some
results looking at activations.
Well, these are recordings
in the brain, or--
No, these are actually in TEM.
So this is-- the left ones
are neurons in the G section,
in the medial entorhinal
cortex part of TEM,
as you vary position.
Cool, OK.
Yeah, and we're going to get--
my last section is about how
these TEM is like--
[INAUDIBLE]
So we'll get to--
hopefully it will be clear,
the links between
the two after that.
OK, we're happy with
that, though, hopefully.
Cool, term is approximately
equal to transformer, yeah.
So you seem to know all of this.
But I guess my notation, at
least we can clarify that.
You got your data, which is
maybe your tokens coming in,
and you got your
positional embedding.
And the positional embedding
will play a very big role here.
That's the E, and together,
they make this vector H.
And these arrive over time.
Yeah, and you got
your attention updates
that you see some similarity
between the key and the query,
and then you add up weighted
values with those similarities.
So we're all happy with that?
And here's the stacked version.
So the basic intuition about how
these parts map onto each other
is that the G is the
positioning coding, as you
may have been able to predict.
The x, or the input tokens.
This guy, when you
put in the memory,
and you try and recall which
memory it's most similar to,
that's the attention part.
And maybe some--
yeah, you attend,
you compare the current GT
to all of the previous GTs,
and you recall the ones with
high similarity structure.
And return the corresponding x.
I've still got 10
minutes, right?
Yeah.
OK.
Maybe some differences-- so I
think I'm going to go through
this between how
you would maybe--
like the normal transformer, and
how to make it map onto this,
are the following.
So the first of
these is the keys
and the queries are the
same at all time points.
So there's no
difference in the matrix
that maps from tokens
to keys and tokens
to queries, same matrix.
And it only depends on
the positional encoding.
OK, so you only recall
memories based on how similar
their positions are.
So yeah, this is key at time
tau equals query at time tau
equals some matrix applied only
to the positional embedding
of time tau.
Then, the values depend
only on this x part.
So some like
factorization of the two,
which is that value at time
tau is like some value matrix.
Only apply to that x part.
So that's the only bit you
want to recall, I guess.
Is that right?
That's right.
And then, it's a causal
transformer in that you only
do attention at things
that have arrived
at time points in the past.
Make sense?
And finally, the perhaps
like weird and interesting
difference is that there's
this path integration going on
in the positional encodings.
So these are the
equivalent of the grid
cells, the G from
the previous bit,
and they're going to be updated
through this matrix that
depends on the actions that
you're taking in the world.
Yeah, so that's basically
the correspondence.
I'm going to go through a little
bit about how the Hopfield
network is approximately
like doing attention
over previous tokens.
So yeah, I was describing to
you before the classic Hopfield
network, which if you remove the
non-linearity, looks like this.
And the mapping, I guess, is
like the hippocampal activity.
The current neural
activity is query.
The set of memories,
themselves, are the key.
You're doing this dot product
to get the current similarity
between the query and the key.
And then you're summing
them up, weighted
by that dot product, all of
the memories that are values.
So that's the simple version.
But actually, these Hopfield
networks are quite bad.
They like-- in some
senses, they tend to fail.
They have low memory
capacity for N neurons.
They have something-- they can
only embed like naught 114 n
memories.
Just like a big result
from statistical physics
in the '80s.
But it's OK, people
have improved this.
The reason that
they're bad, it seems
to be basically that the
overlap between your query
and the memories is too big for
too many memories, you know?
You basically look too
similar to too many things.
So how do you do that?
You like sharpen your
similarity function.
And the way we're
going to sharpen it
is through this function,
and this function
is going to be softmax.
So it's going to
be like, oh, how
similar am I to this
particular pattern,
weighted exponentiated?
And then over how similar am
I to all of the other ones?
So that's our new
measure of similarity.
And that's the my understanding
of the modern Hopfield.
And then, you can
see how this thing--
yeah, it's basically doing
the attention mechanism.
And it's also
biologically plausible.
We'll quickly run
through that, is
that you have some
set of activity, PT,
this like neural activity.
And you're going to compare
that to each chi mu.
And that's through
these memory neurons.
So there's a set of memory
neurons, one for each pattern
that you've memorized, mu.
And the weights to this memory
neuron will be this chi mu.
And then the activity
of this neuron
will be this dot product.
And then you're going to
do divisive normalization
to run this operation
between these neurons.
So like to make them
compete with one another,
and only recall
the memories that
are most similar through--
the most activated according
to this like softmax operation.
And then they'll
project back to the PT,
and produce the
output by summing up
the memories weighted
by this thing,
times the chi mu,
which is the weights.
So the weights out
to the memory neurons
and back to the
hippocampus of both chi mu.
And so that's how you can
biologically plausibly run
this modern Hopfield network.
And so, sorry, yeah?
Any thoughts as to what the
memories that are inputted are?
Like do you attend over every
memory you've ever made?
Probably not.
Probably not, yeah.
I guess somehow, you
have to have knowledge.
In this case, it works
nicely, because we
like wiped this poor
agent's memory every time,
and only memorize things
from the environment.
And so you need
something that gates it,
so that it only looks for things
in the current environment
somehow.
How that happens, I'm not sure.
There are claims that there's
this just shift over time.
The claim is basically that
somehow, as time passes,
the representations just slowly
like rotate, or something.
And then, they're also
embedding something like a time
similarity, as well.
Because the closer
in time you are,
the more you're like in
the same rotated thingy.
So maybe that's a mechanism
to pass a certain time
you don't recall things.
But the evidence and
debate a lot around that.
So other mechanisms like
it, I'm sure are happening.
Maybe context is
another one, actually.
We'll briefly talk about that.
You know, if you know
you're in the same context,
then you can send a
signal, like somehow
in the prefrontal cortex,
work out what kind of setting
am I in?
You can send that
signal back and be like,
oh, make sure you attend
to these ones that
are in the same context.
So yeah, there we go.
Tim Transformer does the job.
A path integrates its
positional encodings,
which is kind of fun.
It computes similarity using
these positional encodings.
And it only compares
to past memories.
But otherwise, it looks a
bit like a transformer setup.
And here's the setup we had--
MEC, LEC, hippocampus,
and places.
Some, yeah, so here's a brief--
the last thing I
think I'm going to say
is that this extends TEM
nicely, because it allows
it-- previously you had
to do this outer product
and flatten, that's a
very dimensionality is
like terrible scaling
with like-- for example,
if you want to do position, what
I saw in the context signal,
suddenly you have to turn
outer product, three vectors,
and flatten that.
That's a much, much bigger
scaling, like N cubed, right?
Rather than what you'd
like to do is just like 3M.
And so this version of TEM
with this new modern Hopfield
network does scale nicely to
adding a context input, as just
another input in what
was previously this
like modern Hopfield network.
So yeah, there's some--
so yeah, our
conclusions is there's
like proved somewhat interesting
as a two-way relationship
from the AI to the neuro site.
We use this new memory model,
this modern Hopfield network,
that has all of
this bit is supposed
to be in the hippocampus.
Whereas previously, we just
had these like memory bits
in the classic Hopfield
network in hippocampus.
So it makes kind of
interesting predictions
about different cell
structures in the hippocampus,
and it just sped
up the code a lot.
From the neuro-- maybe
there's a few things
that are slightly different,
this like learnable recurrent
position encoding.
So people do some of this--
I think they get like
position encodings
and learn an RNN
that updates them.
But maybe this is like
some motivation to try.
For example, they don't
know the weight matrices,
and these weight matrices
are very biased towards--
because they're
invertible, generally.
And things like
that, they're very
biased towards representing
these very clean structures,
like 2D space.
So it might be
interesting there.
The other thing is this is
like one attention layer, only.
And so like somehow, by
using nice recommendations
making the task very easy,
in terms of processing X,
and using the right
positional encoding,
you've got to solve the
task with just one of these.
Also, kind of nice,
and maybe it's
like a nice interpretation, is
that you can go in and really
probe what these neurons
are doing in this network,
and really understand it.
We know that the position
encoding looks like grid cells,
we have a very
deep understanding
of why grid cells
are a useful thing
to have if you're doing
this path integration.
So it hopefully helps
interpret all these things.
Oh, yeah, and if
there was time, I
was going to tell you all
about grid cells, which
are my hobbyhorse.
But don't think there's
time, so I'll stop there.
Excellent.
Any questions?
OK--
A very base question.
So in the very
beginning, those breeds
are linked into one neuron,
or a population of neurons?
These ones?
Those ones?
Yeah, that's one
neuron's response.
Just one neuron?
Yeah.
Wild, it's wild.
Let me tell you more about
the grid cell system.
And you can know--
how can you know
that it's one neuron?
How do you measure it?
Because you got an electrode
stuck in here, right?
And they generally have the
classic measuring technique
is a tetrode, which
is four wires.
And they receive
these spikes, which
are like electrical fluctuations
as a result of the neuron
firing.
And they can triangulate
at that particular spike
that they measured, because
of the pattern of activity
on the four wires has to have
only come from one position.
So they can work
out which neuron
sent that particular spike.
But a set of neurons that
have grid cell patterns.
Lots of neurons have patterns
that are just translated
versions of one another.
So the same grid like
shifted in space.
That's called a module.
And then, there are
sets of modules,
which are the same types of
neurons, but with a lattice
that's much bigger
or much smaller.
And in rats, there's
roughly seven.
So this is a very surprising
crystalline structure
of these seven modules,
within each module,
each neuron is just a translated
version of one another.
Which, yeah, there's a lot of
theory work about why that's
a very sensible thing to do, if
you want to do path integration
and work out where you are
in the environment based
on your velocity signals.
Nice.
Just this thing, you said
this was really fascinating
about the template thing.
This is a product of evolution,
or a product of learning?
Evolution.
It emerges like 10 days after--
in a baby rat's life,
after being born.
So certainly, that
structure seems
to be very biased
to being creative.
Unclear-- we were
talking about how
it was being co-opted
to encode other things,
and so it's debatable
how flexible it is,
or how hard-wired it is.
But it seems-- the evidence
suggests that there's some more
flexibility in the system.
Unclear quite how
it's coding it.
But it'd be cool to get neural
recordings of it and see.
Well, actually, let's
give our speaker
another round of applause.